After being rescued from slavery and
brought to the edge of the Promised Land,
God's people feared the enemies before
them,
instead of trusting the victory God had
promised.
So God sent his people back into the
wilderness.
There, a rebellion rose against Moses'
leadership.
Consequences struck, the earth opened,
fire fell, and plagues spread.
But Aaron and Moses interceded for the
rebellious people,
and the Lord showed mercy.
Now, the journey continues in a dry land
where God's people surround Moses to ask
for water.
Welcome to Mariners Church. My name is
Jared.
I'm so excited to be with you today.
Before we jump into today's message,
I want to take one final moment before we
close out our ministry year.
We have the unique blessing of getting to
hear your stories every single week
about how God has saved you. He has
restored your marriage.
He's provided for you in a time of need.
We hear stories of healings.
The glory of the Lord is constantly on
display.
Your heart is what we care about the most.
We have all kinds of ministries and
programs and groups and studies and teachings.
We have so many things at the church.
All of them are here to help you grow
closer to God,
and I hope you take advantage. I hope you
lean in.
But I don't want you to miss one
significant area
in which God has access to your heart.
Money has a unique grip on us,
and it's through regular giving to the
church,
which is a primary way in which God can
form us
into a person more like Jesus.
That's what I want for my life.
It's what I want for my family, and it's
what I want for you.
So if you're ready to jump into recurring
giving,
I want to invite you to do so.
I'm so grateful for those of you that
already do.
You are a part of the work that God is
doing all around us here at Mariners Church.
If you want to jump in, you can text
online to the number on the screen.
Follow those prompts, and you will be set
up.
All right, let's get into today's message.
I want you to imagine a 10-year-old on a
two-week road trip with his parents.
So you're in a 1988 Suburban, no air
conditioning.
You start in Los Angeles.
You head east to Branson, Missouri, which
is the Disneyland for the retirement community.
You then travel up north into Michigan
and you make your way back west all the
way to Seattle
and then you drive back down to home in
L.A.
That is about 88 hours of continuous
driving over a two-week period.
It's 6,000 miles, and that was the most
extravagant vacation of my entire childhood.
We had these big adventures of going to
antique stores
in which I collected baseball cards I no
longer have.
And the saddest part is iPads weren't even
invented yet.
It was the longest two weeks of my life.
Now can you imagine doing that with kids
today with no devices?
Just in the car, locked in together for
weeks on end.
I can't even make it to L.A., the starting
point,
without my kids asking how much longer and
do we have snacks and stop hitting me.
I mean, cars are chaos with kids.
I don't care if it's 10 minutes or 10
hours.
It's just like, end the misery.
Okay, we're picking up on the story here
of the people of God in Numbers,
and it's a narrative.
We've been watching a story unfold from
where we began just a few weeks ago
to where our story is going to pick up
today.
The people of God have been nomadic.
They have been on the move for 38 years.
far longer than my two-week road trip.
Let's pick up our story today in Numbers
chapter 20.
We're going to start in verse 1.
The entire Israelite community entered the
wilderness of Zin in the first month
and they settled in Kadesh.
Miriam died and was buried there.
So the opening verse gives us the context
of both the location
but also what is happening inside of this
family.
Kadesh is 200 miles north of Egypt.
Let me show you a map here so you can kind
of get an understanding
of where Egypt is in relation to where now
Israel is, modern-day Israel.
Kadesh is sort of right there in the
center,
and they're on their way towards the
promised land,
which is a region known as Canaan.
Now this is the exact location, Kadesh is,
where our message from two weeks ago took
place.
Remember when Eric taught us about the 12
tribes
encamped in a place called Kadesh,
and they elected two scouts from each
tribe.
They were sent into the region called
Canaan,
which is this promised land by God.
But they came back, and they reported of
these giants in the land.
They allowed their fear to take over.
They expressed a lack of trust in God, and
they faced a severe consequence.
Because of their lack of trust in that
story,
40 years is going to be spent following
God in the wilderness.
Now, I almost tripped up on my words.
I don't know if you caught me, but I think
about this as like,
I always think like they were wandering in
the wilderness for 40 years.
But it's not actually wandering.
God is the one who was leading them.
Remember, it was a pillar of smoke by day
and fire by night.
Anytime God moved, the people would
follow.
God led them throughout the entirety of a
generation in the wilderness.
You see, God wanted them.
Because of this consequence of their lack
of trust,
God had them following him until this
unbelieving generation all had died.
Now, Miriam, who is Moses' sister,
her death proves that there was going to
be no special exceptions,
not even for Moses' family.
But the consequence was for them as well.
So the story continues in verse 2.
It says,
So the people of God are frustrated.
And it kind of sounds like they want a
charcuterie board.
But there's real pain that's inside of
this for them.
You see, the children of this prior
generation are now standing
in the same location as the first
rebellion.
This place, Kadesh, is the same place in
which those scouts were sent.
And what is happening?
The children of them, the ones who were
grumbling back then,
now the children are doing the same.
But there is something real that they're
complaining about.
They're saying, we have no water.
And you and I know that three days without
water would be death.
This was a real issue.
Their complaint, though, is almost word
for word
what their parents said decades ago.
That story in Exodus chapter 17.
They say, why did you bring us out of
Egypt to die here?
Now notice who they were quarreling with.
It wasn't with each other.
It wasn't actually God.
They were quarreling with Moses.
You see, the people following after Moses,
they confused Moses to be their provider,
not their leader.
That's going to be a really important
point here.
But Moses is kind of an important figure.
Maybe you can remember.
Moses was raised in the house of Pharaoh.
He was chosen by God to lead his people
out of the Exodus.
You have the amazing stories of the
plagues and the splitting of the Red Sea.
He is the one who provided the Ten
Commandments.
God gave them to him, and he descended
down the mountain to give them.
This was God's guy.
Throughout the whole Old Testament,
you see God in search of a human to
partner with.
His first creation, Adam.
Then we carry on to the stories of
Abraham.
And now we see Moses.
There are others along the way.
And guess what?
There's going to be others to follow.
God wants to partner with someone in order
to repair what we had broken.
So then the story goes on.
So the people are complaining.
They go to Moses, and they say,
We need water.
So what does Moses and Aaron do?
Here's verse 6.
Then Moses and Aaron went from the
presence of the assembly
to the doorway of the tent of meeting,
which is the tabernacle.
That's where God's presence was.
They fell face down, and all the glory of
the Lord appeared to them.
The Lord spoke to Moses,
Take the staff and assemble the community.
You and your brother Aaron are to speak to
the rock while they watch,
and it will yield its water.
You will bring out water for them from the
rock
and provide drink for the community and
their livestock.
So Moses took the staff from the Lord's
presence
just as he had commanded them.
Now, they did the right thing.
Moses and Aaron, they went to God.
They bowed down before him,
and they knew that God is the one who is
ultimately going to provide.
He is the great provider.
He is the sustainer of their life in the
wilderness.
He has been providing for them for
decades,
a generation at this point.
So Moses takes the complaint to the only
place
where complaints belong, to the tent of
meeting,
which is the tabernacle, the very presence
of God.
God gives them instructions.
He tells them exactly what to do.
And then here's verse 10.
Moses and Aaron summoned the assembly in
front of the rock,
and Moses said to them, Listen, you
rebels,
must we bring water out of this rock for
you?
Then Moses raised his hand,
and he struck the rock twice with his
staff,
so that an abundant water gushed out,
and the community and their livestock
drank.
Wow.
I mean, it is a miracle.
This is a miracle what has happened,
but did you catch the problem?
You see, this miracle is God providing.
They're at this point, there are millions
of people.
This is not a little stream flows out of a
rock.
This is an abundant river that can provide
for the people
and for all of their livestock.
Why is it that God did that?
Why did he choose even though something
was wrong in the story?
You see, God was not appeasing the crowd.
This is God providing for his people.
But a plot twist is about to happen.
Look what happens in verse 12.
But the Lord said to Moses and Aaron,
Because you did not trust me to
demonstrate my holiness
in the sight of the Israelites,
you will not bring this assembly into the
land I have given them.
These are the waters of Meribah,
where the Israelites quarreled with the
Lord,
and he demonstrated his holiness to them.
Okay, you're probably like, wait a second.
I've heard this story before.
I don't really remember it ending in that
way.
And you're absolutely right.
This is a parallel story.
You see, Numbers chapter 20, the story we
just read,
is a very similar story to what had
happened years prior,
taking place in Exodus chapter 17.
In fact, let me show you the parallel of
these stories.
You see that God gives instructions in
Exodus 17,
the other story.
He says, strike the rock.
And so what is Moses' action?
He strikes the rock.
And then what is God's response when that
happens?
Water flows.
That's probably the story you remember,
but that's not the story we just read.
Let me show you what happens in Numbers
chapter 20.
God says, speak to the rock.
What was Moses' action?
He strikes the rock.
So then what is God's response?
He prohibits Moses and Aaron from entering
the promised land.
And yet there is one other response from
God.
The water still flows.
You see, God in Numbers chapter 20, he
said,
take your staff, but don't use it.
He says to speak to the rock.
Don't strike the rock.
In Exodus chapter 17, God told him to
strike the rock,
and then water came out.
It was the same problem that they were
facing.
They needed water in both stories.
In fact, it was the same person.
Moses was the one.
And Moses had the same staff.
God said, take your staff.
But then he gave him a different command.
He said, speak to the rock.
Don't actually use your staff.
This staff is kind of an incredible thing.
It's the same staff that turned the Nile
River into blood in the Exodus story.
It's the one that parted the Red Sea.
It's the one that prior had struck the
rock and water flowed.
But God said, take it.
Don't use it.
You see, sometimes obedience for you and I
means picking up that tool
or that thing that we're known for,
but then also setting it back down because
God said something different.
It means surrendering to God and
remembering that the staff,
and this is good for you and I to
remember,
that the staff was only ever as powerful
as God allowed it to be.
God's instructions changed, and Moses
missed it.
Well, he either missed it or he
disregarded it.
Now, we've probably all been in a place
where you've experienced, like,
what got you here won't get you there.
We learn things in our life.
We find ways to do the things that we
enjoy or the discipline that we need.
But sometimes those things hit a ceiling,
and what got us here isn't what's going to
get us there.
This came so real for me as I started
raising children.
If you have kids, you know that each phase
of a child's development
requires a different style of parenting.
What you did when they were infants is not
what you can do when they're toddlers,
and it's definitely different than when
they become teenagers.
Now, the total plot twist is that you
could have two kids in the same age group,
and it still requires two different
approaches to parenting.
What got you to one child is not the same
for the next child.
Now, I have two kids. I very much
experienced this in my own home.
My firstborn, my son, Asher, when he was
told to go to his room,
when he was, like, five, six, seven years
old,
when he was told to go to his room, he
would storm down the hall,
and then he would kind of politely close
his door, and then he'd sit on his bed,
and about 30 seconds later, you'd hear his
sweet little voice go,
Can I come out now?
Well, then as my daughter got into that
age group, and we told her to go to her room,
she said, No.
And so we told her again, Go to your room,
and she said, No.
And so we had to pick her up and put her
in her room,
and then she would yank on that door like
a little personal tornado inside that room.
It was crazy, the differences of our kid.
You see, we had to operate differently
even in the same children in our own house.
Moses experienced this.
You see, what worked once for Moses was
not going to work again.
You may be asking why this is such a grave
offense.
It's a pretty big consequence that Moses
faced,
but you've got to understand from God's
perspective.
Moses put himself in the place of God.
There's a pastor and writer that I love
named Tim Keller, and he said this.
He says that when Moses calls them rebels,
Moses sets himself up as their judge.
He condemned them.
And then in saying, Must we bring you
water?
He sets them up as their deliverer.
Everything Moses did pointed away from God
and actually to himself.
So just as the people confused Moses to be
their provider and not their leader,
Moses was confused as well.
Moses actually believed it, too.
So if Moses' consequence was a plot twist,
like if you didn't see that coming,
the other one is that water came out
anyway.
Like, Moses did the wrong thing.
Moses faced a consequence, and yet God
still provided for the people,
even when his servant disobeyed.
You see, there's this whole generation
that God desires to preserve.
This is kind of dangerous territory if you
think about it.
Just because something works doesn't mean
that God blesses it.
The water flowed and yet the leader,
Moses, he still got disqualified.
Results are not the same as obedience.
You see, the wilderness was not ever
really the problem,
it's the heart.
The problem is not we're short on water,
the problem really in this story is who's
gonna get the glory when the water flows out.
Now, I shared with you two different
stories.
There's the parallel of Exodus 17 and
Numbers chapter 20.
It's two different locations,
and yet, did you notice the name Waters of
Meribah being used?
The Waters of Meribah is a really specific
name.
In fact, it's a name that was given by
Moses at the end of the story in Exodus chapter 17.
Moses names the location Meribah, which
means quarreling or complaining or bitterness
because that's exactly how the people were
acting.
So Moses names the place in Exodus 17
Meribah.
But did you notice that in Numbers chapter
20, it's a different location, and yet it's the same water?
The location in which they're at is called
Kadesh,
which means holy or set apart or sacred
but now it is called the waters of Meribah because of Moses' quarreling with the people.
Two different locations, two different
fights, but bitterness ensues.
You see, God's name is supposed to be holy
in the place called holy, Kadesh,
but Moses gave its bitter name instead.
Now this is a big deal for God.
Holiness is not God being sensitive or
touchy.
Holiness is God being God.
And so to treat a holy God casually is to
misrepresent him to the people who need to know exactly who he is.
Moses misrepresented God to the very
people God was trying to reach.
Now, the relationship between God and
Moses is so important and so fascinating.
If you're right now enjoying the World Cup
like I am,
you probably are watching some of the
commentating that is happening as well.
I love soccer. I've been a soccer fan for
many, many years now.
And so you know that Zlatan is a part of
the commentating staff right now.
And this guy is a global pillar in soccer.
Like the world knows who Zlatan is.
But he's sharing a desk with another guy
named Lexi Lawless.
And Lexi's a former U.S. player.
And I don't mean that in a demeaning way,
but he's not Zlatan, okay?
Zlatan is like a powerhouse,
and then you've got Lexi, who has played
soccer. It's wonderful.
In fact, they both played in the MLS,
which is an important part of the detail here.
But every now and then, you watch Lexi
think he's friends with Zlatan.
He tries to jab him. He tries to kind of
rib him a little bit.
He tries to play jokes on Zlatan,
and that's where you can see the
difference between the two.
Zlatan has nothing to do with it.
I mean, his separation from Lexi is some
of the best nighttime television going on right now.
Here's what happened. They both played for
the MLS back in the day.
Zlatan, while he played for some of the
world's greatest clubs, he finished his career right here on the LA Galaxy.
world's greatest clubs,
he finished his career right here on the
L.A. Galaxy.
And Zlatan's ego is so big that when he
committed to the L.A. Galaxy,
they took an ad out in the L.A. Times.
In fact, you can see right here in this
image, the cover page is him in his Galaxy jersey.
But more importantly, Zlatan himself
wanted the back cover all to himself.
And the text reads just simply, Dear Los
Angeles, you're welcome.
I love it. I love it so much.
Zlatan and Lexi are not on the same level.
They might share a desk together, but they
are different people.
God and Moses exponentially further apart.
God will not stand for Moses taking credit
or reducing God's holiness.
Now, in the grand scheme of where we've
been in the book of Numbers,
this is now the third of three rebellions.
These rebellions each have deepening
consequences, and it's a triplet.
And in fact, you have maybe noticed
throughout Scripture that anytime something comes in threes,
it's like an exclamation point.
When God is called Holy, Holy, Holy,
that's meant to be an exclamation point.
And in these rebellions, it's like a
spiral.
Each rebellion is getting more severe.
Let me show you the graphic that we saw
from week one.
You can see here the 12 tribes, as
instructed in the book of Numbers,
are encamped around the tabernacle.
Right inside between the tribes and the
tabernacle themselves is the Levitical tribe.
We learned about them last week.
And at the center is the tabernacle
itself.
That is the dwelling place of God.
The three rebellions follow these three
concentric circles.
Numbers chapter 13, after traveling 200
miles north from Egypt,
the scouts are sent out.
They come back.
They are terrified.
Their fear and their lack of trust
resulted in 40 years of the wilderness.
That's the outside circle.
Then last week, we saw Korah.
We saw in Numbers chapter 16 that Korah
rose up against Moses and Aaron.
His own pride and jealousy took over, and
the ground swallowed up.
In fact, if you missed that message,
you've got to go back to last week.
Eric's message was amazing.
I want you to hear that.
And now the third rebellion, the inner
circle,
in the exact same location as the first
rebellion,
we are now here at the tabernacle.
These are God's guys, Moses and Aaron.
40 years they've led people through the
wilderness,
and they have arrived back exactly where
it started.
But this time, we see that the inner
circle is susceptible to failure too.
They're so close to the promised land.
In fact, look at this map.
Kadesh is on the border of Canaan, the
promised land,
the place in which they're trying to go.
They traveled 200 miles,
and they're only 80 miles away from being
in the place in which God promised to them.
And this is the place that Moses was
disqualified.
He was prohibited from entering into the
promised land.
And you might be asking yourself,
like, isn't that kind of harsh?
Like, does this feel too harsh?
I don't know.
Let me tell you about how harsh I can be
sometimes.
I recently got the worst haircut of my
life.
And I know what you're probably thinking,
and it kind of hurts because it isn't this
haircut, okay?
It's not this one.
It was a prior one.
But I sat down in the chair to a guy that
I'd never seen before,
and he looks at me and says,
all right, what are we doing here today?
And I kind of explained it.
And he says this.
So your hair, like, swoops forward and
then over.
Like, is that what you want?
And he said it in such a way that I was
like, no, definitely not.
And I said the worst thing you can say to
somebody.
I said, just do whatever you think.
And within 10 seconds, I knew that I was
doomed.
And I also knew I would never return back
to that guy.
You see, Moses, well, for me, that was a
small mistake.
And I will never go back to him.
Maybe that's too harsh.
But Moses did not make a small mistake.
He put himself in the place of God.
He made himself the provider.
He took the credit for what only God could
do.
Now, I want you to understand that this
was a consequence, not a punishment.
What are the differences there?
And I know I'm going to kind of play with
words here a little bit,
but I do think it's important for our own
understanding of God.
As I've shared already, God desired a
human partner.
Moses was God's chosen leader from the
plagues to the splitting of the sea,
the Ten Commandments.
And now in this story, we see that the
mighty are able to fall.
There's a book that Jim Collins wrote in
2009 called
How the Mighty Fall.
It's easier than some people realize.
When building a company, in the pursuit of
more,
they start to overreach into what is
waiting for them.
They have moved outside of their core
competence,
and they are now operating in a place of
risk.
And so when the time comes, there's a
little downturn in their profitability.
They start to grasp for salvation, and
that's Jim Collins' words.
They start to look for that silver bullet,
the new leader, the bold pivot,
this radical restructure.
And then most fail.
They slip into irrelevance or death.
And here's his closing point.
If leaders can catch decline early enough,
and name it honestly,
and they can return to the disciplines
that produced greatness in the first place,
rather than reaching for an outside savior
themselves,
they would not fall or fail.
Moses did not catch his decline early
enough.
He allowed the pressure and the demands to
bend his actions,
and his consequences feel harsh.
But Moses is not an average person.
Moses is not like you and I.
This is the leader of the people of God.
The holiness of God is not something to be
messed with.
So God needed a partner, and even Moses
failed.
Even Moses was able to fail.
Now, that failure is both an illustration
and an example for us,
but it's also a reminder that at the end
of the day,
every human was eventually going to fail.
And so what does God do?
You know, eventually God sent his own son
to be the God-man,
fully God, fully man, who would not fail
or fall.
Jesus is the rock, and it is on this
foundation that the church was built.
The victory of Jesus is our victory.
That the punishment has been satisfied.
The punishment was paid by Jesus.
The wrath was poured out on him.
We are human, and we fail too.
And our failure is not final, and our
punishment has already been paid.
That is the grace of Jesus.
That is the beauty of having a
relationship with him.
While we may fail, and there may be
consequences for our actions,
we will not face punishment because Jesus
has on our behalf.
Now, you're probably thinking, wasn't this
story all about people being thirsty?
And the answer is yes.
And inevitably, only Jesus, who is the
rock, can be the provider of living water.
There's one story in the New Testament, as
Jesus was with his closest 12 disciples.
In Matthew chapter 16, it says this.
When Jesus came to the region of Caesarea
Philippi, he asked his disciples,
who do people say that the Son of Man is?
And they replied, some say John the
Baptist, others Elijah, still others Jeremiah,
or one of the prophets.
But you, he asked them, who do you say I
am?
And Simon Peter answered, you are the
Messiah, the Son of the living God.
And Jesus responded, blessed are you,
Simon son of Jonah,
because flesh and blood did not reveal
this to you, but my Father in heaven.
And I also say to you that you are Peter,
and on this rock I will build my church,
and the gates of Hades will not overpower
it.
And I will give you the keys of the
kingdom of heaven.
Let's contrast these two stories.
Moses at Kadesh, now called Meribah, God
said, speak to the rock,
and Moses spoke to the people instead.
And what he said was words of bitterness.
He said, listen, you rebels, must we bring
water out of this rock for you?
And then the verdict came from God,
because you, Moses and Aaron,
did not trust me to demonstrate my
holiness in the sight of the Israelites.
You will not bring this assembly into the
land.
But Peter at Caesarea Philippi, when Jesus
said, who do you say that I am?
Peter spoke, and he said, on this
confession, he says,
you are the Messiah, the son of the living
God.
He named Christ correctly in front of the
disciples,
in front of this rock, which was filled
with false gods and pagan worship.
And then the commission from Jesus came.
Jesus says to them, on this rock,
so on the confession that Peter made about
Jesus being the Messiah,
I will build my church, and I will give
you the kingdom of heaven.
Peter rightly represented God in front of
people,
and was given the keys to the kingdom.
You see, Moses spoke to the people, and he
faced a consequence.
When Jesus was with Peter, Peter said, you
are the Messiah.
And Jesus says, it is on that confession
that I will build the church,
the church that you and I are a part of
today,
and you will be given the keys of the
kingdom.
The contrast is both beautiful, and it is
a warning sign for all of us.
You see, it's inside of the wilderness
that rebellions can happen.
And I think already you know that if Moses
can fail, so can you and I.
And when challenges come, when our needs
go unmet,
when the dreams that you have for your
life are met with opposition,
this is where we are most susceptible to
rebellion.
This is when your perseverance begins to
wane.
When your frustration increases, and
hopelessness starts to creep in,
and you start to ask yourself, what am I
doing wrong?
Why can't I get out of this rut? What's
wrong with me?
How long can that frustration go before it
starts to become grumbling?
It's really only a matter of time, if not
carefully managed,
that we will begin to grumble, just like
the people of God.
That we've seen all throughout the book of
Numbers.
You see, their grumbling ultimately
becomes an indictment against God.
We would be better off in slavery. You
have brought us here to die.
That is what the people of God has
declared throughout the book of Numbers.
So let me ask you, have your circumstances
caused you to rebel against God?
Maybe it's not an outward rebellion,
although that happens too.
We run from God, we pursue other things,
we go after our own desires.
But occasionally, these are inward
rebellions, where we start to doubt.
We start to question in such a way that
starts to become unhealthy.
We start to seek after different things,
and we begin, inside of our own hearts,
we begin to rebel almost exactly like the
three rebellions that we saw in Numbers.
Maybe you're like the scouts in Numbers
chapter 13,
where they had a fear of what was out
there,
and a lack of trust that God would take
care of them.
Or perhaps like Korah from Numbers 16,
where they allowed pride and jealousy to
consume them,
to go after their leaders and to put
themselves in their place.
Or maybe you're like Moses and Aaron,
where you look at your life, and you are
taking credit for God's activity.
That bank account, your job, you look at
the things in which you have in your life,
and you think you are the one who created
those things.
Where are you most susceptible for
rebellion?
Because of Jesus, our rebellion does not
lead to punishment,
and I'm so grateful for that.
When you and I approach God with humility,
when we confess our rebellion,
we remind ourselves that He is God, and we
are not.
Then we are reminded that it's on that
confession of faith
that we are standing on the rock that is
Jesus.
He is our foundation. He is our provider,
our sustainer.
He is our King. Amen and Amen.
I am so grateful for you.
This is a chance where you and I get to
sing to our King Jesus,
the one on which we stand.